Perry Hall Improvement Association records
Perry Hall Improvement Association records
1945-1986
1945 1986
Coll002
Perry Hall Improvement Association
5 boxes (5.5 linear feet)
5 boxes
5.5 linear feet
This collection contains the papers of the Perry Hall Improvement Association (PHIA), a local community advocacy group founded in 1945 by the residents of Perry Hall, Maryland, a residential community located in Baltimore County. The collection contains by-laws, histories, rosters, correspondence, minutes, research and case files, financial and legal documents, publications, clippings, and copies of local laws and regulations. Also included is a written history of Perry Hall that the group published in 1970 entitled "An Invitation to Memory"; a copy is available in Series IX.
University of Maryland, Baltimore County Albin O. Kuhn Library and Gallery UMBC 1000 Hilltop Circle Baltimore, MD 21250 410-455-2353 speccoll@umbc.edu
This collection of the records and documents from the Perry Hall Improvement Association (PHIA) covers the period from the establishment of the Association in 1945 through 1986. The majority of the material covers the period during the 1960’s and 1970’s when Baltimore County was experiencing rapid expansion. Extensive rezoning was underway to accommodate population growth and businesses wishing to expand into the county in areas formerly exclusively residential. The PHIA took an active interest in the rezoning process, acting as advocate for individual property owners fighting zoning changes and the allocation of residential property for commercial use. Case files of zoning cases or appeals in which the Association had an interest are present. Much of the correspondence in the collection is between the PHIA and the different offices of the county involved with zoning and county services. There are reports and bulletins from county and state offices, the zoning commission and planning board, primarily from the late 1960’s and 1970’s. Copies of zoning laws and building codes are available from different periods.
Internal documents of the Association cover the period from 1945 through 1981. The by-laws and amendments and the business license of the Association are present. Minutes of the regular monthly meetings are generally complete for 1945 through 1981. Minutes of the Board of Directors and Special Committees are sporadic, primarily in the late 1950s and 1960s. Rosters of the membership of the association, both active and inactive, dues paid lists and attendance sheets are available for most of the period through the 1970’s. Treasurers’ reports and other financial records are present for individual years. Programs from Association events and a history of Perry Hall compiled and published by the Association are present. Clippings from local newspapers are included but not well documented, often without dates of publication. Miscellaneous material and files on subjects or groups peripheral to the association are grouped as research files.
The Perry Hall Improvement Association was formed in 1945 to “beautify, safeguard, encourage and improve the physical, moral and spiritual living conditions of the people who reside in or are influenced by the community of Perry Hall.” The association defined the area as “power lines on Belair Road near St. Joseph’s Church, on South, by Gunpowder Falls on North Joppa Road & Cowenton Avenue on East to power lines on Joppa Road near Simms Avenue.” The first meeting was held on July 31, 1945. The Association started in response to the proposed establishment of a cemetery on Joppa Road near Belair Road. This commercial venture was successfully defeated; the first of the Association’s many attempts to balance commercial and residential interests in the area.
Through the 1940s and ‘50s the Association successfully campaigned for reduced speed limits near the Perry Hall School, got street signs installed by the state on Route 40, and mounted several successful protests against rezoning for light industry and waste disposal (auto junkyard and garbage dump). Contacts with other area associations were established and although membership and attendance fell through the late 1950s the association continued to monitor and protest commercial development in the area.
The 1960s saw renewed interest in the Association and its activities. Successful lobbying resulted in the establishment of the Perry Hall branch of the Baltimore County public library and the formal change of name from Fullerton to Perry Hall by the Post Office. Traffic, roadway maintenance and zoning continued to be the major areas of concern. After 1965, zoning becomes the predominant area of interest for the Association. The Baltimore County rezoning plan, driven by the increase in population in the area and a desire to draw more commercial interests included many changes for the Perry Hall area. The history of the Association through the late 1960s and 1970s is one of almost constant protest or appeal of various zoning decisions by the Baltimore County Planning Board. In 1970, the Association celebrated its 25th anniversary with the publication of a history of the area, “An Invitation to Memory” and in 1976 was responsible for coordinating many of the Bicentennial celebrations in the area.
The 1980s again saw a decline in interest and membership in the Association. This may have been because rezoning disputes had been resolved for the most part and/or because increased population, housing and commercial interests in the area had moderated Perry Hall’s strictly residential emphasis. The proliferation of other interest groups in the area and of umbrella organizations serving the entire county presumably reduced the appeal of the Association.
Organized into eleven series: Series I. Bylaws, 1945-1984. Series II. Histories, 1945-1976. Series III. Rosters, 1945-1984. Series IV. Minutes, 1945-1981. Series V. Financial and Legal Documents, 1948-1980. Series VI. Correspondence, 1945-1986. Series VII. Laws and Regulations, 1955-1980. Series VIII. Case Files, 1963-1980. Series IX. Publications, 1970-1988. Series X. Clippings, 1960-1980, n.d. Series XI. Research Files, 1945-1986.
Bylaws
Histories
Rosters
Minutes
Financial & Legal Documents
Correspondence
Laws & Regulations
Case Files
Publications
Clippings
Research Files
No restrictions.
Finding aid available.
MSS 1994-04; The papers of the Perry Hall Improvement Association (PHIA) was donated in 1994 by Mrs. Genevieve Buetttner, a long time member of the PHIA Board of Directors.
Civic improvement Maryland Perry Hall (Md.) History; Community organization Maryland Perry Hall History; Perry Hall (Md.) History
Perry Hall Improvement Association (PHIA) homepage. Accessed November 12, 2015.
- Series I. Bylaws, 1945-1984; 1 folder
  Bylaws and amendments thereto of the Association.
  - By-Laws (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Series II. Histories, 1945-1976; 2 folders (.25 linear feet)
  Includes written history of the Association from 1948-1957, programs, publicity and related material from Association events, 1947-1976.
  - Histories: Association (PHIA) History: 1945-1969 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Histories: Association events and publicity: 1947-1976 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Series III. Rosters, 1945-1984; 11 folders (.5 linear feet)
  Lists of members, active and inactive; meeting attendance sheets; dues paid lists; directories; Presidents list. Arranged in chronological order.
  - Rosters: Member directory: 1945-1955 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Rosters: Member lists / Dues paid: 1945-1955 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Rosters: Member lists / Dues paid: 1963-1978 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Rosters: Inactive member list: January 1, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Rosters: Member directory & Inactive list: 1945-1974 (original "President's Book") (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Rosters: Attendance sheets: 1973-1976 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Rosters: Members telephone directory: 1978 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Rosters: Member lists / Dues paid: 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Rosters: Member lists / Dues paid: 1981-1984 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Rosters: Association Presidents: 1945-1978 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Rosters: Baltimore County Planning Board: 1975 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Series IV. Minutes, 1945-1981; 8 folders (.5 linear feet)
  Minutes of regular monthly meetings, Board of Directors meetings, Special Committee meetings. Arranged in chronological order.
  - Minutes: Regular meetings: July 31, 1945-Dec. 6, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Minutes: Regular meetings: July 31, 1945-Dec. 6, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Minutes: Regular meetings: Jan. 2, 1958-Dec. 12, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Minutes: Regular meetings: Jan. 9, 1964-DEc. 10, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Minutes: Regular meetings: Jan. 14, 1971-Dec. 13, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Minutes: Regular meetings: Jan. 10, 1974-Nov. 11, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Minutes: Regular meetings: Feb. 10, 1977-Nov. 12, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Minutes: Special Meetings (Board of Governors & Special Committees: 1953-1970 (Irregular) (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Series V. Financial & Legal Documents, 1948-1980; 10 folders (.75 linear feet)
  Attorney retainer agreements, bank statements, checkbook stubs, business license, income tax forms, receipts, letters of authority. Arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Financial & Legal Documents: Attorney retainer agreement & statements: 1971-1976 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Financial & Legal Documents: Auditors' reports (Irregular) (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Financial & Legal Documents: Bank statements: 1970-1976 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Financial & Legal Documents: Business license & Lease agreements (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Financial & Legal Documents: Checkbook stubs: Mar. 1948-Dec. 1957 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Financial & Legal Documents: Letters of Authority: 1949-1980 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Financial & Legal Documents: Receipts: 1970-1980 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Financial & Legal Documents: State tax forms: 1948-1975 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Financial & Legal Documents: Treasurers' reports: 1960-1970 (Incomplete) (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Financial & Legal Documents: Zoning Fund: 1946 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Series VI. Correspondence, 1945-1986; 14 folders (.75 linear feet)
  Form letters and fliers; correspondence with state and county offices; general correspondence. Arranged chronologically within subjects.
  - Correspondence: Events & Speakers: 1948-1969 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Correspondence: Form letters & fliers: Baltimore County: 1970-1980 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Correspondence: Form letters & fliers: Local area groups: 1969-1982 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Correspondence: Form letters & fliers: PHIA: 1949-1982 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence: General: 1945-1986 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence: State & County: 1945-1959 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: State & County: 1960-1970 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence: State & County: 1971-1980 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence: State & County: 1981-1984 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence: State & County: Belair Road Study: 1979 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence: State & County: Carroll Manor School: 1973 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence: State & County: State Roads Commission: 1945-1955 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence: State & County: State Roads Commission: 1968-1978 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence: U.S. Post Office: 1961-1980 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Series VII. Laws and Regulations, 1955-1980; 8 folders (.5 linear feet)
  Baltimore County rules and regulations; Home Rule Charter; Zoning regulations; Individual slip laws. Arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Histories: Association (PHIA) History: 1945-1969 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Histories: Association events and publicity: 1947-1976 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Laws & Regulations: Baltimore Co. Bond Referendums: 1976, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Laws & Regulations: Baltimore Co. Code: 1961 Cummulative Supplement (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Laws & Regulations: Baltimore Co. Home Rule Charter: 1956 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Laws & Regulations: Baltimore Co. Zoning Regulations: 1960 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Laws & Regulations: Baltimore Co. Proposed Zoning Amendments: 1973 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Laws & Regulations: Baltimore Co. Zoning Regulations: 1975 Revision (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Laws & Regulations: Baltimore Co. miscellaneous bills: 1965-1982 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Laws & Regulations: Maryland Law Governing Aeronautics: 1966 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Series VIII. Case Files, 1963-1980; 31 folders (1 linear feet)
  Case files of zoning cases, including all correspondence, judgements and appeals. Legal cases other than zoning (minimal). Arranged alphabetically by plaintiff.
  - Cases: Liquor Board: Kahl Tavern: 1972 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Cases: Liquor Board: Persing application: 1976 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Cases: Zoning: Aston: 74-76 RX (1973); 77-156/157-X (1977) folder (a) (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Cases: Zoning: Aston: 74-76 RX (1973); 77-156/157-X (1977) folder (b) (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Cases: Zoning: Berg: 79-47-V (1973) (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Cases: Zoning: Betz: 74-205-R (1974) (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Cases: Zoning: Columbia Club/Knights of Columbus Hall: 79-47-V (1979) (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Cases: Zoning: Dansberger: 76-57-V (1976) (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Cases: Zoning: Diakoulas: 74-206-R (1974) (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Cases: Zoning: Gaudetsky: 63-102 (1963) (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Cases: Zoning: Kahl: 72-229-RX (1972) (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Cases: Zoning: Kishter: 75-58-R (1974) (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Cases: Zoning: Lauman: 78-247-XA (1978) (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Cases: Zoning: Loch Lomond Inc (Resolution): 1960 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Cases: Zoning: Maryland National Bank: 77-131-XSPH (1977) (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Cases: Zoning: Mills: 76-344/345-V (1978) (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Cases: Zoning: Mills: 76-344/345-V (1978) (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Cases: Zoning: Myers Estate: 72-49-R (1972) (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Cases: Zoning: NPM Inc.: 73-201-R (1973) (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Cases: Zoning: Nothview Associates: 82-109-X (1982) (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Cases: Zoning: Northview Shopping Center: 77-13-V (1976) (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Cases: Zoning: Nottingham Village Inc.: 71-174/175-RX (1971); 72-50-R (1972) (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Cases: Zoning: Perry Hall Associates: 75-218-R (1975) (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Cases: Zoning: Presbyterian Church: 5772-RX (1963) (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Cases: Zoning: Schroeder: 82-241-X (1981) (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Cases: Zoning: Story: 5615-RX (1963) (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Cases: Zoning: Universal Housing & Development: 74-73-R (1973); 74-217-R (1976) (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Cases: Zoning: W.I.T.H. Inc.: 76-35-X (1975) (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Cases: Zoning: Summary of Zoning Cases 1971-1973 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Cases: Zoning: Miscellaneous notes and material (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Cases: Zoning: Miscellaneous out of area cases not pursued (Box 2, Folder 50)
- Series IX. Publications, 1970-1984; bulk 1970-1980; 26 folders (.75 linear feet)
  Newsletters; planning and zoning reports; information brochures; Association publications. Arranged chronologically within subject.
  - Publications: Cable TV franchise application summary(Baltimore Co.): 1972 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Publications: Directories: Baltimore Co. organizations: 1970-1975 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Publications: Maps: Miscellaneous (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Publications: Newsletters & Announcements: Bicentennial Committee: 1976 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Publications: Newsletters: Maryland Dept. of ransportation "Transit Action": 1975 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Publications: Newsletters: PHIA Newsletter: 1962-1963 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Publications: Newsletters: Whitemartsh Run Watershed Newsletter: 1974-1976 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Publications: Newsletters: Miscellaneous (other area groups) (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Publications: Planning & Zoning: 1967-1969 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Publications: Planning & Zoning: 1970 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Publications: Planning & Zoning: 1971 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Publications: Planning & Zoning: 1974-1973 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Publications: Planning & Zoning: 1974-1975 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Publications: Planning & Zoning: 1975 (continued) (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Publications: Planning & Zoning: 1976 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Publications: Planning & Zoning: 1977 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Publications: Planning & Zoning: 1978 (a) (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Publications: Planning & Zoning: 1978 (b) (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Publications: Planning & Zoning: 1979-1981 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Publications: Planning & Zoning: 1982 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Publications: Planning & Zoning: 1984 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Publications: Planning & Zoning: 1988 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Publications: Private printing: PHIA "An Invitation to Memory": PHIA 25th anniversary (1970) (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Publications: Miscellaneous: County (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Publications: Miscellaneous: State (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Publications: Miscellaneous: State: Department of Transportation (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Series X. Clippings, 1960-1980, undated; bulk 1970-1980; 7 folders (.3 linear feet)
  Articles and photographs from local newspapers. Arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Clippings: Baltimore Co. budget: 1975 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Clippings: Perry Hall Post Office: 1962 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Clippings: Zoning: 1961-1964 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Clippings: Zoning: 1967-1971 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Clippings: Zoning: 1972-1977 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Clippings: Zoning: 1978-1983 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Clippings: Miscellaneous: undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Series XI. Research Files, 1945-1986; 9 folders (.3 linear feet)
  Primarily material on other area groups active during the same period. Files may contain any of the following: correspondence, clippings, pamphlets, brochures and incidental material. Arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Research file: Baltimore Co. Planning Board: 1981-1982 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Research file: Baltimore Co. schools (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Research file: Citizen Planning & Housing Association: 1969-1976 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Research file: Council of Civic Associations of Baltimore Co. (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Research file: Northeast Coordinating Council (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Research file: Notes: PHIA: Miscellaneous (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Research file: Perry Hall Library (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Research file: Title search: Bishops' Inn (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Research file: Whitemarsh Run (Box 5, Folder 9)